Guide to the Kirby Smith Howlett, Jr. Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Kirby Smith Howlett, Jr. papers
1934-1965
MS 1412
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(4 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence and writings documenting Kirby Smith Howlett's research on and treatment of tuberculosis, particularly the testing of streptomycin. Also included are materials for Howlett's work with the American Trudeau Society and the American Review of Tuberculosis.
Howlett, Kirby Smith, 1904-1974
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Joseph L. Howlett, 1985.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Kirby Smith Howlett, Jr. Papers are composed of correspondence, writings, and other papers from Howlett's professional files. The papers document that portion of Howlett's career as phthisiologist when breakthroughs in drug therapy portended the eradication of tuberculosis. Howlett, as assistant superintendent of the Laurel Heights Hospital in Shelton, Connecticut, was one of the first doctors to conduct a study of the effectiveness of streptomycin in treating this dreaded disease, and the papers primarily document this phase of tuberculosis research.
The papers are arranged by correspondent, organization, or topic and are listed alphabetically. The earliest papers date from the 1930s when Howlett studied the use of oleothorax in treating tuberculosis. Howlett authored a chapter on the therapy, copies of which are found in folders 43-46. See also the correspondence with John Alexander (folder 2) and the subject file on oleothorax therapy (folder 33).
Howlett conducted much of his research under the auspices of the American Trudeau Society. Serving on the committees on therapy and on chemotherapy, Howlett took part in the organization and implementation of clinical trials of streptomycin. See particularly the files for the American Trudeau Society (folders 7-19) and for committee chairmen H. Corwin Hinshaw (folders 22-25) and. H. McLeod Riggins (folders 34-35) as well as the subject file on streptomycin (folder 39). Various writings by Howlett on streptomycin research will be found in folders 47-54.
Howlett served as president of the American Trudeau Society (1949-1950) and was active in the society in other ways. The files for the society document various projects and concerns through correspondence with office staff, minutes of meetings, and correspondence with committee and society members. Similar material. exists in the files for the American Review of Tuberculosis. Howlett was a frequent contributor to that journal and served on its editorial board.
The Kirby Smith Howlett, Jr. Papers were given to the Yale University Library in 1985 by Howlett's son Joseph L. Howlett.
Biographical / Historical
Kirby Smith Howlett, Jr. was a physician and phthisiologist, a specialist in the treatment of tuberculosis. He spent his entire professional career at the Laurel Heights Hospital in Shelton, Connecticut.
American Review of Tuberculosis; Drugs -- Testing; Medicine; Streptomycin; Tuberculosis -- Chemotherapy; Tuberculosis -- Research; Physicians; Alexander, John, 1891-; Hinshaw, H. Corwin (Horton Corwin), 1902-2000; Howlett, Kirby Smith, 1904-1974; McDermott, Walsh, 1909-1981; Riggins, H. McLeod; Sadusk, Joseph F.; American Trudeau Society; Laurel Heights Hospital (Shelton, Conn.); National Tuberculosis Association
- Inventory
  - Abbott Research Laboratories, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alexander, John, 1935-1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1946-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - American Trudeau Society, 1943-1952 (Box 1, Folder 7-16)
  - American Trudeau Society, 1953-1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - American Trudeau Society. Eastern Section, 1951-1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Barnwell, John B.
    General
    See also: box 3, folder 41
    See also: box 1, folders 7-16
  - Connecticut State Tuberculosis Commission, 1947-1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Hinshaw, H. Corwin, 1943-1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 22-25)
  - Hoffman-LaRoche Inc., 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - International Union Against Tuberculosis, 1950, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - McDermott, Walsh, 1948-1952 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    General note
    See also: box 1, folders 3-6
  - Merck & Company, Inc., 1948-1950. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - National Institute of Health, 1946-1952, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    See also: MS Common Folio 53
  - National Tuberculosis Association, 1944-1958 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - New York Tuberculosis and Health Association, Inc., 1954, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Oleothorax therapy, 1934-1935 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Riggins, H. McLeod, 1944-1950, undated (Box 3, Folder 34-35)
    See also: box 2, folder 32
  - Rimifon and Marsilid treatment, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    See also: box 2, folder 26
    See also: box 2, folder 28
  - Sadusk, Joseph F., Jr., 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Steenken, William, Jr., 1947-1950 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    See also: box 2, folders 22-25 box 2, folder 29 box 2, folder 31 box 3, folder 37 box 3, folder 38 box 3, folder 41
  - Streptomycin, 1946-1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    See also: box 2, folders 22-25
    See also: box 2, folder 29
    See also: box 2, folder 31
    See also: box 3, folder 37
    See also: box 3, folder 38
  - Tuberculosis -- diagnostic standards, epidemiological aspects, testing, 1941-1955 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - United States. Veterans Administration, 1946-1962 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Writings, 1935-1947 (Box 3, Folder 42-48)
  - Writings, 1948-1965, undated (Box 4, Folder 49-54)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Tuberculosis center photographs (Box 5)